knowledge is power
[Music]
just tell me maybe more about your show
like maybe what's the vision of your
show what's it about and then we can
just dive in to whatever you want to
talk about yeah yeah of course so it
kind of started as basically a mental
health podcast and by that i mean just
kind of listening to people tell their
story listening to people kind of give
their perspective on life and what
they've gone through or what they know
and trying to
kind of provide little little useful
pieces of information for listeners
because i was watching a lot of podcasts
and listening to a lot of interviews and
finding that random sentences you know
58 minutes into a podcast would just be
profound to me
personally so um it's been that and then
kind of expanded and grown and i
interviewed a lot of uh you know
just different types of artists you know
metal bands lead singer metal band
rappers
carpenters professional bodybuilders
authors just all different types of
people um so yeah just basically
everybody has you know a unique
interesting perspective or view and we
could all kind of learn from it it's
kind of the
premise
that's good yeah yeah
so uh let's start with let's start with
just kind of like a bio from you just uh
maybe kind of how you got into um a lot
of these subjects as well
yeah so those philosophical subjects are
things that i'd like to think about um i
think i started
my philosophy hobby i was thinking about
philosophy maybe 10 years ago it's just
you know on the side i love thinking
about it i love thinking through these
questions
but my day job is as a software product
manager i work
now at a
fintech company um just started a
contract two weeks ago so that's my day
job
i like i work with developers to build
software
and then i've got a side project or side
business where i make mobile apps for
podcasters and content creators
so i reach out to podcasters
see if they want to have a conversation
but also tell them about my business
um yeah that's what i do for my job for
my profession
and on the side
i love having deep conversations i don't
have enough of them
my wife is not too keen on having them
with me so whoever wants to have
conversations on these topics i am
always ready and willing
yeah i mean you definitely went the
brave route by just doing let's let's do
podcasts together like that's that's
pretty cool that you did that yeah it
doesn't have to be a podcast but i mean
i figured i'll reach out to podcasters
who are also my target customers so you
kill two birds with one stone just have
a conversation get to know
uh you folks and see where the
conversation goes yeah yeah that's
brilliant okay so what is it what is it
to you about philosophy and kind of
questioning um you know our existence
why we're here consciousness any of
these things like what is it really
about that that triggers you that i love
the fact well i think
when i went to grad school for whatever
reason
um i
it opened up to me the fact that there
are so many hidden assumptions we have
so many beliefs that are just underneath
everything and they're unexamined so
that was like the peak into it maybe
10 years ago now like i said um
but i love thinking through the
what we call presuppositions or
underlying assumptions that hold
everything else up and i don't think
people think about them enough but
they're really important and really
interesting when you think through
what's the basis the foundation or the
ground
of a lot of our beliefs
and so we can dive into any of any of
the ones that you want to
yeah yeah any and all of them um so what
do what do you think like do we have is
consciousness built through evolution um
do you think it's more
um is it part of part of matter itself
like what is what and why is
consciousness a thing yeah so
consciousness is really interesting that
ties into i think the free will thing
as i think about free will and i think
as people live their lives
the assumption is and the working
assumption is that it's a real thing we
do have free will we make
real decisions on our own
that's like the common sense assumption
and um working
working definition i think people just
assume
i also believe that we have genuine free
will we're making real decisions here
we're not robots we're not determined by
our
physical laws right going on in our
brains
we're making real choices and the
choices therefore
matter
we're responsible for those decisions
and we can go into morality as a
consequence but
sticking with free will
i think
uh
freedom when i think about it in the way
that we just talked about it like
genuine free will it's not a part of
nature when i think about
physics the laws of physics and the laws
of chemistry
there's no freedom involved there
there's cause and effect
we have the laws of nature right these
are
these are descriptions of the way
physical reality behaves
you can't break the laws of nature they
break you it's like the word law is kind
of a misnomer there but
it's just the way things are
and that leads me to believe like if we
do have genuine free will we're making
real decisions real choices
and that's
something that's outside of physical
reality it's something different
um one one step further as i think about
freedom is i think freedom is necessary
for
rationality
so when we say we believe something
um
on rational grounds or like you know
let's say i believe in something based
on
the evidence i see
i'm making a choice there i'm i'm
choosing to believe something because of
good reasons and and the evidence that
i've
gathered
that's a choice
and that's what makes it reasonable
that's what makes it rational
so if i didn't have a choice if free
will was an illusion or
it's just like a useful fiction or
something
then all of my beliefs by definition
wouldn't be rational
even the belief
that i don't have free genuine free will
i don't know if you followed that last
step but it's like circular when i think
about that it's
the belief that you're free your free
will
the belief that you don't have free will
and your free will is irrational your
free will is not
um
not genuine
that belief in itself
is irrational
and
therefore i think that belief
you can't hold that belief uh you can't
justify holding that belief
logically
all right right
okay so okay so when it
as far as our pool
to
pull from
uh
like like the the series of choices that
we have so sam harris kind of has um
a
a practice or something that he's done
on podcasts or conversations where um he
basically asks the person say like
think of um think of a mammal the first
thing that pops in your head whatever it
is
and then he's like so why didn't you
think of say a giraffe why didn't you
think of a gorilla or whatever it is um
just thinking of the bank of animals
that we happen to know of because of our
experience because of what we've seen
because of what we've heard
we only we only have like a pool to pull
from we only have like a a box of
experiences
up into this point to uh you know a grab
bag of prior experiences so i didn't
have if you were to say um say say you
chose giraffe
for example and you had never heard of a
gorilla you'd never seen a gorilla you
didn't know it existed you didn't have
the free will to
pull gorilla if you didn't know that it
existed what do you think about that
you don't have the free will well i
guess i mean that makes sense to me yeah
you don't have the freedom to choose an
option you're not aware of
that seems fine to me like
yeah we don't know
everything we only know a little bit of
what's out there and
but we can choose
so
that's interesting so the first thought
that comes to your head yeah i don't
think there's a choice involved there i
don't think everything we do is free um
so
the first thought that i got was dolphin
i didn't choose that it just came up
so i don't think there's choice involved
there and yeah i agree like you don't
have the
choice to choose something you're not
even aware of it's not even in the pool
of your experience or content so right
yeah yeah
sam harris kind of talks like that and
it makes me think because i hadn't
thought about it until he said something
um it does make me think it is kind of a
you know it's kind of a zooming in
unnecessarily in a weird way because
it's like okay of course we weren't
talking about the things that we haven't
experienced you know so it almost is
when i feel like the way that you talk
about free will is just based off of our
it's of course only based off of our
experiences because that's what we're
trying to to answer right you know we're
not
we're talking about our lived experience
and if we have free will within our own
limits which of course we're in our own
limits that's how we're even
to the point of the conversation but i
think what's fascinating about
that example is there are so many things
in our lives that we have no control
over
so many thoughts like just think about
uh your interests i think jordan
peterson talks about this all the time
did you choose your interests
i don't think so i mean we have an
affinity toward things
and activities topics
right i don't think i had a choice in
that
and he says like do you choose your
interests or do your interests choose
you
ooh
i like that i think i think they choose
us in a way like yeah anyway i did i
didn't control you can't choose to love
anybody
um or like fall in love with anybody i
think that just happens to you and
they're so i feel like probably most of
our experiences are not
you know they're not rational
choices decisions they're just happening
to us
right yeah yeah and then we're trying to
piece together the puzzle you know our
ego is just trying to form like here's
why it happened and yes of course i love
this i made this decision um yeah it
kind of kind of is interesting because
it's not say you fall in love with
dancing at a young age and you're seven
years old it's not like when you were
six you were saying to yourself i'm
going to fall in love with dancing next
year you know it's you don't you don't
plan it you just have an experience one
whole day of you just seeing someone
dancing or you watched it on tv or you
heard about it whatever something that
makes you kind of attached to the thing
that like that you're interested in you
know
that is that is very um that it's very
intriguing because
yeah yeah really thinking if if our
interests choose us you know it is it
does kind of see because so okay so what
do you think about um determinism so
along with you know kind of the contrast
of free will because maybe there's a
little bit of a mix of both of that are
possible what do you think
i mean i think
um
the physical reality
is determined if you're just talking
about molecules in motion
that seems to me
determined by the laws of physics and
the laws of nature
the interesting thing is like we human
beings are in nature
and
um if we
have free will like genuine free will
then we're like this
we're an element of indeterminism within
a determined
universe
that seems to me
to jive with what i hear is going on in
quantum physics i think there are
elements of indeterminism within
um physical reality or descriptions of
physical reality
so it's probably a combination right
in quantum physics
like
physical laws seem to be determined but
there are elements of indeterminism
within it so
the reality is probably
both and we just don't understand how to
put them together
[Music]
but they seem to be together
like human beings are in a physically
determined universe if we have free will
then we're yeah agents of indeterminism
and yet
um
we're embedded and
uh what's the word yeah we're living
inside of a physical physically
determined universe
yeah so what is it we
we have free will within a box
or something yeah
and that seems to be
uh like
it's not unusual like we have games
right we play chess that's there's
freedom within
the confines of the rules of the game
like that seems to be a common thing
across different domains
yeah i mean maybe it is uh we're always
kind of looking for structure amongst
chaos we're looking for and we're
innately looking for patterns um and we
can kind of exist and live within those
patterns so the patterns are the the
rules on the chessboard you can or
cannot yes or no hardline
do or do not these things and it creates
a structure that we can actually play
the game within and maybe we're kind of
doing that same thing with life
i think so yeah cause like the laws of
nature you can't go outside the laws of
nature you can't break them they're
gonna break you right yeah so those are
the
restraints of the game
but there's a lot of choice yeah
do you think we will ever um just as a
thought experiment do you think we'll
ever break outside of any of our laws do
you think we'll ever have any sort of
because i think um like with the quantum
quantum physics the the
the quantum physics stuff is so
fascinating and um and i know this is a
kind of a ridiculous jump but like the
marvel
um universe they talk about all this
this different dimension stuff it really
kind of like pokes where we're at with
science anyway and it does kind of make
me think that
maybe there is a way in which humans
could
jump
whatever that means you know forward in
consciousness or or evolution or some
sort of jump from whatever whatever it
was that went from monkeys to us maybe
there could be another thing like that
some sort of jump and it's something to
do um
uh
uh with our with our with our current
reality kind of changing have you have
you thought about any of that i think um
uh there are more dimensions than we
are capable of
perceiving
uh i think that's just a fact right like
we can't hear
above or beyond certain frequencies we
can't see
right above or beyond certain um of the
the visual spectrum
so our physical
uh organs
just
by the nature of what they are
we're seeing only a slice of reality
there's a lot more that we're just not
perceiving there's so much going on that
we're just not aware of
so
yeah i can see us um
like expanding our senses sense
capabilities to perceive beyond what we
can now
whether that happens through technology
or
some other mechanism like you said
evolution
maybe our brains will
evolve or change in a way that we can
perceive
more than we can now i think that's
yeah
yeah i mean that's happened right like
with
with microscopes we can see
and telescopes we see far more than we
could within with the naked eye
maybe and that that's an analogy of what
can happen
in the future
right yeah like our tools do kind of
just become extensions of us they're
kind of like
you know they're just a way of reaching
our arms to be a little bit longer into
what humans are are capable of doing
yeah yeah that's that's super
interesting it's also very interesting
thing about the contrast with zooming in
really really far and then we we zoom
out really really far to see and it just
continuously expands right no matter
which way we go it just continues to uh
to expand or like like as the technology
gets better the the more the deeper we
can go the farther out we can we can
look it's so interesting yeah it's
amazing it seems like there's no limit
to
um
what there is to discover
i mean yeah from the very small to the
to the sides of the universe i still
can't get my head around the fact that i
mean the universe has a size and you
there you know it is expanding
um
yeah so it's that's kind of beyond what
i can comprehend right because our our
brain you know we hear a billion or hear
a trillion or we hear infinity and we're
like yeah and that's that's a lot and
but really our brain doesn't of course
we can't comprehend that you know we
don't really think of wow what what is a
billion of something or what is a you
know what what does infinity really mean
for something to go on forever like our
brains don't really have a experiential
understanding of it so yeah
so that's that kind of um leads me to
to this thought
um
so
assuming that we've evolved right um
our brains our bodies are
adapted for survival in a particular
environment
let's just say like the
uh
the plains of africa like we all human
beings let's say originated from africa
and so our bodies
haven't changed in the
however many thousands of years that
we've
uh become human beings
so we're like evolve for a particular
environment
it seems to me
so strange
and fascinating
that
the brain of a primate the body and
brain number primate that's involved in
this particular environment
is able to comprehend
the
the size of the universe
quantum physics
um
very advanced mathematics that i have no
idea like there's so creativity making
music and businesses like
it seems unreal unreal that
um
yeah that
the brain evolved for that particular
natural environment
could do all this and
i feel like um
why trust the brain why trust let's just
say you know the primate brain why would
you trust the primate brain
um
so outside of its natural element
exploring abstract concepts that are so
far removed from what it was
adapted for which is survival within
that particular national environment why
trust any of these things that we have
we're thinking of right
so
for me i feel like
uh you might call it the naturalistic
um
explanation for
consciousness maybe
um
there's something
like it it undermines it somehow i feel
like there's less
justification to trust
um the deliverances of our cognitive
faculties
on that evolutionary view
um
i don't know if that made sense like
yeah yeah so so why yeah basically why
would
you know it seems obvious why it's
important to uh give time and effort
into not getting eaten by a lion or
finding finding
food to eat you know keeping keeping
alive survival so like the jump from
survival to
you know looking up at the stars
wondering
where you are in comparison to that and
wondering what that is and wondering
what you are like what would that um
what what is that that awareness i guess
like where where does awareness come
from and why
why does it come
you know it's a have you ever heard of
the uh stoned ape theory
oh is that something to do with like
taking psychedelic uh substances yeah
yeah i don't know the full thing yeah
yeah so um terence mckenna talks about
it uh essentially we're apes living in
trees um surviving that way and then
after a while we end up getting out of
the trees or something brings us out of
the trees for whatever reason and we
start looking for food on the ground
hunting more whatever we're away from
the trees and we start following um cows
flipping over cow pies looking for food
start noticing that's where you know in
manure is where psychedelics grow
and then we realize because of survival
there's different there's certain little
subtle things that psychedelics like
magic mushrooms for example would give
you better uh visual acuity
so this makes you better at hunting
it would
potentially connect your tribe more in
in different ways they probably had some
sort of like orgy situation when it came
to these apes when they were doing all
these psychedelics um so basically it
kind of like had all these positive
effects as far as
keeping a group of of apes together
and so over you know hundreds of
thousands of years or whatever it is um
they continue to follow behind
bowls and bowls and um cows and and flip
over the manure and take psychedelics
and that's kind of how consciousness
started to form they started realizing
things started having language started
noticing that when they would eat food
here and throw it on throw the seeds on
the ground when they come back a year
later in season there'd be crops growing
yeah yeah and then they start having a
memory bank to kind of build those
things on so that's kind of the the
stone deep theory of sorts i mean when i
hear that it's a nice story
i i i don't don't buy it huh i don't
feel like that's at all plausible it's
an i mean it's a story
well so what do you what do you think it
is like what what do you think
what is the birth of consciousness to
you then do you have any let me think
about language for a little bit i
thought a little bit about language um
when i think about what language is and
i have a son like a six-year-old boy now
wow just the work it takes to teach
a language to a child
it's it's an enormous amount of effort
and time to teach language to someone
who doesn't have a language
um
so to imagine a situation where a
language could somehow evolve from
nothing
i think is an is an insurmountable gap
for one
so
given the implausibility of a language
coming from nothing
um
and just another example of that is like
when we look at the animal kingdom there
are communication systems like birds
have chirping systems signals and all
this but i think when people analyze the
way animals communicate compared to the
way human beings communicate through
language
i think there's a fundamental difference
between a language and these signal
signaling systems
so when i think about what a language is
and the fact that new languages are
always born out of existing languages
um
i think that
um i think language needs to
pre-exist there has to be a language
before any new languages can come to be
and that language whatever that new
language is
it has to be taught
like parents have to teach their kids
how to speak the language
of their society
and so there's like an enormous amount
like i said of investment
time effort patience that goes into
anyone acquiring a language
so
like i'm a christian so when i think
about like
the bible and
god being described as in the beginning
was the word i was like whoa
that's interesting
in the beginning was language
and he's described as like our father
wow i wonder if adam and eve were like
these
apes or primates humans homo sapiens
and god had to
adopt them and teach them language like
the enormous amount of investment and
time and love it takes to teach language
to
a primate maybe the primate had the
cognitive capabilities i'm sure like you
and i do right we have the cognitive
capability to pick up language
um
the fact that the faculties are there
but
language acquisition doesn't
just happen it takes
it picks a relationship and it takes a
loving relationship
for that to
happen
and so yeah that's that's my my position
is
um
yeah in the beginning was language in
the beginning was the word
and um that's prob that that's the
beginning of consciousness and once you
have language then you have
consciousness because i don't think you
can be self-aware without the word i
if you don't have the word i in whatever
language
you've acquired
i don't think you can
you have self-consciousness you have
self-awareness like they're tied
together right the word
and um
the self-awareness
i think are tied together so so i kind
of
i i kind of think that
the eye
was formed from still this same survival
technique i think
that when there's some sort of apes apes
hunting
um uh or whatever you know
we're we're essentially
we're going to do things that are going
to increase our chances of survival
right we're going to do things like like
i was saying you know how the
psychedelics would increase the chances
of people working together you know apes
working together and whatnot uh their
visual acuity i think after a while we
would probably have to start pointing if
you're on a hunt you're hunting a boar
you're a group of eight apes and you're
hunting a boar i have no idea if they
actually hunt for how this works but uh
eventually hundreds and hundreds of
years you would start to notice and pick
up i think
when
you do this with your finger you take
your hand this thing is called a hand
they wouldn't know it they haven't
labeled it yet but they are moving a
part of their limbs and pointing over
there or they're gesturing or they're
they're
they're indicating you know we're using
our our body's verbal language
and then that after a while after a long
time starts to form words because we
start to label things we start to
point we start to say
uh you know like
something that indicates good or bad
danger
food
there's a lion or there's a bore
whatever it is so we're pointing over
more and more years we start uh pointing
this is a banana we start making
different mouth noises to indicate the
survival thing has now gone on to
long-term survival in this scenario i'm
not sure uh
but
oh and then eventually what had to
happen if we're labeling things we're
labeling things for survival this is
good or this is bad here's where the
water is here's where you put the seeds
you go over here eventually we have to
start doing you we point at each other
now we have a name now we have a when i
point at you you're uh uh you're a thing
and that's kind of the birth of the ego
that's kind of the birth of the eye in a
lot of ways
what do you think about that i think
again that's it's a it's a story yeah i
don't think there are any examples we
can point to to validate that story
yeah um there are it's like they were
they were writing that down at that
point obviously i mean there were still
like this there are so many animals
in the world right and
we're the only ones
why why should it be that we are the
only ones
if that story is plausible if that
progression is plausible why are human
beings the only ones that have developed
language
um
the guerrillas have been around for as
long as we have right every other animal
has been around as long as human beings
have
if that's a if that process you've just
described is a natural
process
then
i would expect to see other
animals having gone that route yes but
um at least similar you know
because we're because we're so far we
really are so far away from all other
animals you know we're not just at the
top of the food chain we've like we've
left the food chain we're not like we
have power over all the all the other
animals so it is it is very interesting
right like why
why would humans or the thing after apes
be chosen in such a way biologically
we're not very different from
we're we're very similar right 99 what
percent of our dna
is exactly the same as a chimpanzee
right
so there's nothing really biologically
that different from us to other animals
other life
but yeah we've left orbit like we've
left um
the orbit of the animal kingdom
and i think language is
is like the primary uh differentiator
um
so so you you believe that
so you believe that there was so
like you said there was the word so what
would you say um
like how did god learn the word like how
does he know the word not maybe not who
taught it to him but like what what is
that like why does that exist why would
god exist with the word to give it to us
even though yeah i feel like
the definition of god that
i'm working with is he is this
pre-existent
consciousness
so he is the origin of consciousness the
origin of language he is the word
he is language it's yeah it's it's
pretty abstract at that point but like
there's nothing before him right he is
god he's the ultimate reality
and if and the ultimate reality if if
our view if my view is correct
the ultimate reality is conscious the
ultimate reality
is personal
the ultimate reality is loving like all
these attributes of god um describe
ultimate reality
whereas other world views like let's say
buddhism ultimate reality is unconscious
and impersonal
right so it's a very clear distinction
between world views
um
that i hold yeah
yeah i i find that
i'm pretty fascinated by really all of
the the different religious beliefs and
how we came to to all of our different
beliefs how different cultures had for
so long believed in so many different
things and then they shifted or whatever
it's all just so fascinating i always
try to wonder what are they all kind of
pointing at you know like maybe we have
different language maybe we have
different words for it um but like what
is this thing within humans that that
we have some sort of desire for a higher
power for meaning for purpose for um
direction
or um
you know and and then also the fact that
for whatever strange reason you know
love and kindness and joy and uh you
know all these like good positive
emotions seem to connect us closer to to
that that feeling of of meaning of
purpose you know it is it there's
there's no denial that
that
you know love and god are so so
intertwined you know
i think in our western
uh
societies we tie god and love together
because
of the christian tradition and heritage
in the west
i don't think that's true in other
and in other
geographies other traditions
but um
but i yeah when you talk about purpose
and meaning
i think that is universal i think it's
proven
i just finished a book um called man
search for meaning by victor frenkel
have you heard of this one
it's a pretty famous one i think um
viktor frankl was a psychiatrist
who was in auschwitz and he lived
through that and he wrote a book about
that just right after he got out of it
but
that's just one book
no one can live without a purpose
without a sense of purpose
you will die you will kill yourself if
you don't have a sense of purpose
people don't think about it very much
but
um
i think that's a fact like without hope
uh everything becomes meaningless and
we die so it's not a
hope it seems to be like a survival
mechanism it's an adaptation that
if it is an adaptation it's
it helps us survive
i think it it's fascinating to
to realize that we all think of
ourselves as the hero of our own story
we live inside a story we just do
we are the main character in our own
stories everyone else has their own
stories
we fit everything into like a meta story
so i think story is something also
really
embedded within our human being
so thinking narratively
thinking ourselves as heroes you know
within our own stories
um
i think all pointing to the fact that
there is
an ultimate story and our our lives do
matter within that big story
and it is
like even the word history has the word
story in it
his story yeah
um
we can't help it it's it's
it's the way we are we we structure
these things into stories
but i mean i think that points to the
fact that there is an ultimate story
there is a meta-narrative and we are
living into it
but that only makes sense i think from a
theistic worldview where there is a god
he is the author the creator
he has a plan for not just our lives
individually but a plan for the the
entire human race there is a
structure
a story structure to this whole thing
yeah i like that i like that so so uh
thinking along the lines of like jordan
peterson's lectures he talks about um he
kind of gives us the examples of how we
live through a um a hero's journey uh
and he gives examples i think through
like lion king and peter pan um i'm not
sure if you've if you've listened to
those lectures um
if not
oh yeah awesome cool yeah it's been a
while since i've touched on those but i
remember really liking those um and i
like to think about
you know what is the reason what is the
reason why you know the marvel movies
are so popular right now what is the
reason why we do love disney so much i
think it's because they really are
speaking to something within each of us
you know it's it's hard it's hard to
quantify and explain it with a capital t
truth of like this is something that is
is 100 true amongst all humans um when
it comes to like us needing some sort of
purpose or story that we're following or
following some sort of hero's journey
but it's
man it really does seem to be true you
know people's lives are a lot more
fulfilling when they feel as if they
have some sort of sense of of purpose or
meaning within within their own scope do
you think
that a lot of what we're going through
you know our depression rates are crazy
high right now um there's a lot of
you know there's a lot of like kind of
madness going on in in some ways um
right now do you think a lot of people
are kind of living without purpose
right now yeah i think so and so the
book i'm reading was written in like
and the author was saying even back then
he there was a survey i think it said
like
maybe 60 or 70 of the people that were
surveyed back then
felt like there was no one
or
nothing that they would die for
um so like the meaning problem was a
problem back then it's i'm sure it's
even worse now
people
[Music]
um
people need meaning they need a purpose
but um
it's hard to
to find one to hold on to
uh for your entire life and i think as
we get older and we pursue we you know i
think naturally we do have short-term
purposes
like when we're young we're going after
different things
but as we pursue those things over the
years as we get older and older
um
those things tend to lose their grip on
us and we begin to question or we've you
know
climbing up the wrong ladder are you
pursuing the wrong things
and then when you get to that point of
your thinking
then
a lot of people feel lost like okay then
what am i what should i be
living for
what is my purpose and the more
questions you ask at that point i think
uh the more confusing things can get
um
but i think for for most people that
they're they grow up within a tradition
so if you grow up within a muslim
tradition for example or a hindu
tradition or it's religion for the most
part right if you grow up within a
christian tradition
those questions tend to be answered for
you from your tradition
you can adopt them
more readily you want to question them
and make them your own but there's a set
of answers there for you to consider
i think a lot of people
um as they become
atheist
or lose their religion and like break
away from their traditions
it becomes a lot harder because there
isn't
some ready set of
values and purposes you can kind of
consider
if you're an atheist
then there really is
no long-term purpose that's just a brute
fact there is no purpose to your life
ultimately
um there's no purpose to the human race
ultimately the universe itself is going
to
experience a heat death right
nothing
matters
on that worldview so it can be very
depressing if you think if you think
about that um for too long and so i
don't think people tend to want to think
about that
[Music]
yeah yeah i mean it's
i i do find when
there is this innate feeling of nihilism
that that kind of takes over when you
when you really you just have this
everything's meaningless my life's
meaningless we're all going to die
it's like
there's like a flip side of it that
really can bring your life
it makes you
see the joy and beauty that you already
have you know and and it is kind of like
okay yeah yeah maybe this is a short
sliver of of life but that is it like
what a gift then what what a gift it is
that
you know this infinite universe this
infinite um uh solar system you know all
this crazy time that we're alive within
all of times is we're just a blip on the
radar as far as we know but isn't that
awesome isn't that amazing like what it
what a gift to be able to be just a blip
on the radar
um
do you think uh you had mentioned
morality at the at the beginning as well
what do you gain out of out out of
um having a sense of morality values
i feel like i didn't
i kind of had like a spiritual awakening
you know basically just being able to
admit to myself that there's something
bigger than my own dang ego you know um
so i i kind of
had this
i don't think that i had as many stern
values or morals or realized when like
you know like if you lie or you say
something dishonest or you say something
hurtful it actually hurts you later on
it's kind of that that hell that's
inside of you you know the the reactions
to living without values and morals that
sort of thing
when that kind of sparked within me it
it gave me oh yeah values and morals are
actually important it is kind of good to
have bumpers up on your life and give
yourself a little bit of a direction at
what you're facing how do you
john um like
how do values and morals and these sorts
of things help you in your life
i think the moral laws are
uh objective and i think they're
normative so meaning
we are obligated to obey them
so i thought about this actually last
weekend
i was thinking about the different kinds
of laws there are
in the universe so
at the top i thought of stuff like
logical laws there are laws of logic and
laws of mathematics
two plus two equals four it's a law of
arithmetic
um
these laws
are
uh
rules for proper thinking so that
they're like they're within the abstract
realm
you you can break them but you you can
only break them by accident
so
i think of the example like
if you don't know that two plus two
equals four you can make a math error
you can put five there but once you
understand that two plus two equals four
um and you you believe that to be true
it is impossible from that point forward
for you to believe anything else like
you can't break
that
law of logic once you understand it like
knowing it pretty much binds you to it
you can try as much as you like to
believe that two plus two equals two
thousand
you're not going to be able to break
that law
so that was
one area of law i was thinking about
um they exist
um
you can't you can break them but only by
accident
and then at the bottom i was thinking
about like the laws of nature and i
don't like the word law but like these
are descriptions of
physical
uh the behavior of the physical world
they're just descriptive
um you can't break them
you're never gonna break the law of
gravity right if you try to you're gonna
it's gonna break you
so there's no
um breaking the laws of nature
and in the middle
it's funny like we live in the space
between the heavens and the earth like
we live in that middle space and i was
thinking about the laws of morality are
so interesting because
they connect the abstract realm with the
physical
realm because their law
the laws of morality are both
rules for proper thinking and rules for
proper acting they're like both and they
live in like this middle space where we
live we live in the middle space between
our our abstract thinking
world and the world of acting and
behavior
so i was thinking about that and
um
yeah like the rules of morality
the laws of morality are unique in that
you can know what the right thing is to
do
and you can consciously disobey you can
break that you can know you can know
something is true and then you can also
disobey it you can break it so it's
unlike the laws of logic it's unlike the
laws of physics
it's pretty special it's there in the
middle it's it's where we live
um
and then going back to like think about
free will since we do have free will
assuming we do have free will genuine
the genuine capacity to make choices
um
when we
disobey a moral law when we break it we
become guilty and i think that that word
guilt
i think again it kind of all ties back
to freedom guilt is only real
when you when you have the freedom to
break a moral law
and so this whole concept of guilt
um
is only possible
because we have genuine freedom
and then
guilt leads to punishment right if you
break the laws of america you are then
liable to being
arrested
judged sentenced right punished for that
so all these concepts around
being guilty
and then
receiving
some kind of punishment or reward for
our
behavior
all kind of ties back to
freedom as well
um how does it help me in my life
so again i think world world view plays
a big part here um i think a lot of
different world views
view the moral law of their tradition as
laws of proper behavior right and like
you if you do these things and follow
these laws
at the end of your life
god will weigh you in the skills of his
righteousness and if your good deeds
outweigh your bad deeds then you get to
go to heaven if your bad deeds that way
you're a good deeds then you go to
hell
so
um and that's kind of also related to
what you just said like you said
you've discovered that following these
moral laws in the end come back to
reward me come back to help me it's
almost like
an
adaptive thing
it's self-serving to be a good person
also helps me live a better life maybe a
more successful more happy life
so
i find within that view it still kind of
turns around
and ends in self-interest
like to do a good thing because it
helps me in the end
is still in the end self-interested it's
still kind of selfish
if i were to walk an old lady across the
street because
i thought you know what in the end god's
gonna give me brownie points or in the
end this is gonna come back to me in
some good way
it's you're doing that
kind of for self-interested reasons
and so there's something off-putting
about that for me
i think um
what the christian worldview
says is
we do good not because it's gonna buy us
some reward or
come back to us in some positive way we
obey these laws of morality
we obey god's law because
it's like an expression of thanksgiving
almost it's an expression of
the fact that he loves us and he's
already forgiven us of all our guilt we
don't have to earn our way to being
right with him
it's just we're doing these things for
purely for others now i can walk that
lady across the street not because it's
going to come back to me in some good
way or not because i'm going to get
brownie points or go to heaven because i
do that i can walk that person across
the street or do any good deed
because
um i want to help that person it's
completely other focused it's not
self-interested
but those are some thoughts around
morality maybe you can respond to any of
those yeah yeah those are all nice man
um yeah there really is something
special about stepping outside of
ourselves and our own um
you know our we all have our own level
of constant neuroticism of some sorts i
think you know um so when we step
outside of ourselves and we could be of
service to someone else service to
others not not to our own um ends
um you know the if things do happen you
know you do this nice thing and ends up
having something else come back to you
that's a plus that's not you don't think
about the reward right that's the that's
just something that if it happens it
happens that's awesome but you're not
doing it to to score those browning
points like you said um
john we are getting kind of up here in
time and i feel like we could talk for
hours honestly but um i do have to uh
get going to work here and not too long
so i do want to round the corner a
little bit uh i was just kind of
thinking of a good question um
to ask you you know you you contemplate
a lot of these things it seems like like
you you said you enjoy
philosophy you like thinking about these
things you like um
only contemplating them but you you're
also you know you're you're a father
you're a businessman
if you had to maybe talk back to your 18
year old self your 20 year old self um
or even just someone like him you know
if any of the listeners maybe are that
age you know they're younger if you had
some like blanket statement advice of
how to see the world how to live um what
what to do what not to do do you have
anything that that pops to mind
yeah i mean what pops to mind is um
don't do things because you think
it's the thing everyone else is doing
like i went to college right after high
school i probably shouldn't have gone to
college right out of high school i
probably should have worked
um
grown emotionally socially
made money
like
been more independent just grown as a
person before i decided to commit to a
four-year education somewhere in a major
that
um was going to be relevant
to my career
so i think
if i were to talk to talk to myself at
18 i'd say don't go right into school
work for a couple of years figure
yourself out discover what your
interests are like your real interests
explore those
and then if you decide to go back to
school choose choose something that you
really want to study so you don't waste
your time and money
in school
studying something that you're not
really interested in
and
yeah also i didn't have a work ethic so
like going to school without a work
ethic you're trying to build a work
ethic while
being in school it's it's
difficult right
you don't know why you're there like
so
i guess
take the time to discover your
purpose
discover your interests
and try to make decisions in your life
that
get you closer to to your purpose
and then you'll save a lot of time and a
lot of money
like floundering yeah i took a lot of my
20s
just yeah just kind of floating
um
not knowing what i wanted to do with my
life
i don't regret i don't regret a lot of
that but if i were to go back
i'd want to get clarity earlier on
so i can make more progress in the time
that
i've had
yeah yeah yeah i think that's a pretty
good answer man it's basically just
yeah find yourself see what you want
even before you just decide on something
that's so you know put you into so much
debt too for sure uh i think it would
have been kind of cool to as soon as i
turned 18 to just you know
sell everything that's too big to fit
into into a van and just go travel
around for a few years you know i mean
obviously that's the that's the pipe
dream daydream it's a little bit more
complicated than that but it really
would i mean being a young age and just
learning about the world through that
lens and just being humble enough to
sleep in your car or whatever it is for
a little while you probably learn a lot
about yourself and what you want and
what you don't want you know
i think so yeah i mean people can get to
these insights i think in a lot of
different ways
there's no like yeah no
one right way to
discover
yourself
um
but yeah taking the time and being
intentional about it i think is worth it
when you're young
yeah and like don't feel pressured to
live up to
uh the expectations
and get the expectations of your
parents or family or friend group or
whatever culture like we're living
inside expectations all the time
but i think that can be oppressive
and so just yeah i mean it helps me even
though it's kind of morbid to realize
that life is really short
and
there just isn't enough time
to be worrying about living up to other
people's expectations
you want to find well i want to find my
purpose
and i think i have now and i want to
live into my purpose
as fully as i can every day and i mean
and that's it
it brings a lot of
just simplicity to my thought life
and just my regular my normal life my
day to day
and um
yeah life is short we don't know how
much time we have left and it's it's
going to be shorter than you expect it's
going to be shorter than i expect
it it's always the case whether i'm 60
or 70 or 80 or 90 it's always going to
be shorter than i expect i think
yeah man beautifully said beautifully
said i
i appreciate your time and i appreciate
all of your answers and uh in your
inquiries you know i i like i like that
we're able to kind of both kind of think
through some thoughts and and have an
unstructured good conversation man so
really thank you again for for being
willing to do this thanks jacob thank
you for the opportunity and let's do it
again anytime
yeah yeah sounds good man we'll uh we'll
be in touch via email and whatnot and
we'll uh we'll get together again okay
sounds good take care yeah take care
listeners take care of yourself drink
some water stretch love yourself and
we'll see you later have a good one
at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power
you